Ajay Kumar Dwivedi

A ajaydwivedi.com
Nagpur, Maharashtra, India

♀ github.com/imajaydwivedi
■ linkedin.com/in/imajaydwivedi

⟨ (+91) 703-231-2749
 □ ajay.dwivedi2007@gmail.com

Professional Summary

With over 14 years of experience, I optimize SQL Server and PostgreSQL databases and build DevOps CI/CD Pipelines to automate Infra with scripting tools like PowerShell, Python, Ansible and GitHub Actions.

Skills

Databases: SQLServer, PostgreSQL, SQLite, RDS, Managed Instance, Aurora

Programming Languages:

SQL,

PowerShell,

Python,

JavaScript,

HTML /

CSS,

Shell Scripting

Tools and Frameworks: Git, Linux, Ansible, Flask, Django, GitHub Actions, VS Code, Grafana, Prometheus, KVM

Virtualization, Container, Podman, Docker, Ubuntu, RHEL, PowerShell DSC, Infrastructure as Code (IaC)

Cloud Platforms: AWS, Azure

High Availability & Disaster Recovery: Clustering, Availability Groups, Mirroring, Log Shipping, Replication, Disk

Stripping, RAID, Multi Subnet Setup

Languages: English (proficient), Hindi (native)

Certifications

Microsoft Certified Professional - Database Querying
 Microsoft Certified Professional - Database Administration
 BrentOzarUnlimited Mastering SQLServer
 SQLSkills Blackbelt Professional
 Oct 2013
 Nov 2022
 Jun 2023

Experience

Senior Site Reliability Engineer

AngelOne

Feb 2022 - Present

- Optimized 10x SQL Server performance with D.E.A.T.H Methodology.
- Saved 1400 hrs/year by automating Transparent Data Encryption (TDE).
- Reduced 80% alerts with query tuning by fixing problems like Ascending Key, Kitchen Sink design, un-even threading, distributed query plans, MSTVFs, etc.
- Reduced 90% incidents by building monitoring and alerting system using PowerShell & Python.

Database Reliability Engineer

Arcesium

May 2020 - Feb 2022

- Resolved 100s of incidents by moving 38 TB AG databases with PowerShell.
- Automated/Upgraded 30 Critical SQLClusters/AGs in 12 hours avoiding week long downtime.
- Improved database relibility with automated ScriptOut of entire SQLServer Instances for Disaster Recovery.

Senior SQL DBA

TiVo

Feb 2018 - May 2020

- Saved 40+ hours by automating SQLServer deployment and configuration using PowerShell.
- Reduced 80% transactional replication issues with latency infra.
- Reduced 80% performance incidents by building Delta Index Defragmentation automation for replicated & HADR databases.

Senior SQL DBA

United Health Group

Oct 2016 - Feb 2018

- Saved \$1 million/year via DB Space Capacity Automation.
- Improved 50% performance issues with reduced VLDBs maintenance time.

Senior SQL Developer

Ericsson Global

Jun 2015 - Oct 2016

- 3x Performance Improvement via advanced query optimization like Recursive CTE and Table Partitioning.
- Lead 18+ developers for best practices and guidelines.

SQL DBA Developer

TATA Consultancy Services

Mar 2011 - Jun 2015

- Moved 250+ large tables with each having billions of records using SSIS in 45 hours.
- Built data warehouse ETL pipelines using Pentaho & Kettle for high volume Liquor Retail stores.
- Saved 20+ hours/week by Automating core DBA tasks using dynamic SQL.

Education

Bachelor of Engineering in Electronics & Communication Engineering

Jul 2006 - Jun 2010

RustamJi Institue of Technology

Gwalior, Madhya Pradesh

Awards and Honors

Projects

SQLMonitor: Open source Enterprise grade SQLServer monitoring tool

Jan 2021 - Present

- Built using TSQL, PowerShell, Python, and Grafana.
- Successfully monitoring 500+ SQLServers across environments.
- Sends alerts to Slack, PagerDuty or Email
- Inbuilt auto action to Clear & Resolve

HadrSync: PowerShell module that synchronizes all objects across Replicas in Availability Groups

Jan 2021 - Present

- Ensures zero sync issues during failovers/Drs.
- Detects & synchronizes even delta changes like changes in passwords, definition etc.

Availability

Notice Period: 90 Days

Relocation: Open to Relocation

Remote: Open to remote opportunities

FINAL NOTE

I am passionate about designing efficient database systems and solving complex performance challenges. I help organisations build robust, fully automated infrastructure with PowerShell, Python and Ansible.